Hannah Weller

Research interests: the role of biomechanical constraints in life history evolution; paths of least resistance in the evolution of new traits; image processing in organismal biology, with a focus on methods development for quantifying color and pattern.

Education

2019—2023 (ex- PhD, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology

pected) Brown University (Providence, RI)

Thesis: How much does functional morphology matter to the evolution of mouthbrooding?

2017—2019 Transitional M.Sc., Ecology and Evolutionary Biology

Brown University (Providence, RI)

Thesis: How do feeding adaptations influence the convergent evolution of mouthbrooding?

2012—2016 Honors B.Sc., Biology

University of Chicago (Chicago, IL)

Thesis: Winnowing in the eartheater cichlids

Awards and Fellowships

January 2022 Doctoral Dissertation Enhancement Grant

\$10,000, Bushnell Fund at Brown University

April 2019 Graduate Research Fellowship

\$138,000, National Science Foundation

December 2018 Field Museum Visiting Scientist Scholarship

\$1,500, Field Museum of Natural History

May 2017 Presidential Fellowship

\$108,000, Brown University

June 2015 Jeff Metcalf Undergraduate Research Fellowship

\$5,000, Marine Biological Laboratory

March 2015 Elected to Phi Beta Kappa Society

September 2014 Best Presentation, Undergraduate Research Symposium

\$150, University of Chicago

June 2014 Elliott and Eileen Hinkes Research Fellowship

\$4,000, University of Chicago

Peer-reviewed publications

Weller, H.I., Hiller, A.E., Van Belleghem, S.M., and Lord, N.P. (2022). Recolorize: flexible color segmentation of biological images. In review at eLife. Preprint DOI: https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.04.03.486906.

Weller, H.I., López-Fernández, H., McMahan, C.D., and Brainerd, E.L. (2022). Relaxed feeding constraints facilitate the evolution of mouthbrooding in Neotropical cichlids. The American Naturalist. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1086/719235.

Capano, J.G., Boback, S.M., Weller, H.I., Cieri, R.L., Zemer, C.F., and Brainerd, E.L. (2022). Modular lung ventilation in *Boa constrictor*. Journal of Experimental Biology. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1242/jeb.243119.

Tumulty, J.P., Miller, S.E., Van Belleghem, S.M., **Weller, H.I.**, Jernigan, C.M., Vincent, S., Staudenraus, R.J., Legan, A.W., Polnaszek, T.J., Uy, F.M.K, Walton, A., and Sheehan, M.J. (2021). Evidence for a selective link between cooperation and individual recognition. In review. Preprint DOI: https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.09.07.459327.

Weller, H.I., Olsen, A., Camp, A.L., Hernandez, L.P., Manafzadeh, A.R., and Brainerd, E.L. (2020). An XROMM study of intra-oral transport and swallowing in catfish. Integrative Organismal Biology. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1093/iob/obaa018.

Cohen, K.E., **Weller, H.I.**, Westneat, M.W., and Summers, A.P (2020). The Evolutionary Continuum of Functional Homodonty to Heterodonty in the Dentition of *Halichoeres* Wrasses. Integrative and Comparative Biology. https://doi.org/10.1093/icb/icaa137.

Weller, H.I.*, Hooper, S.E.*, and Amelon, S.K* (2020). Countcolors, an R package for quantification of the fluorescence emitted by Pseudogymnoascus destructans lesions on the wing membranes of hibernating bats. Journal of Wildlife Diseases. https://doi.org/10.7589/2019-09-231

*These authors contributed equally to this work.

Cohen, K.E., **Weller**, **H.I.**, and Summers, A.P. (2020). Not your father's homodonty—stress, tooth shape, and the functional homodont. Journal of Anatomy. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1111/joa.13248

van Meer, N.M., **Weller, H.I.**, Manafzadeh, A.R., Kaczmarek, E.B., Scott, B., Gussekloo, S.W.S, Wilga, C.D., Brainerd, E.B., and Camp, A.L. (2019). Intra-oropharyngeal food transport and swallowing in white-spotted bamboo sharks. Journal of Experimental Biology. DOI: 10.1242/jeb.201426

Weller, H.I., and Westneat, M.W. (2019). Quantitative color profiling of digital images with earth mover's distance using the R package colordistance. PeerJ. DOI: 10.7717/peerj.6398

Weller, H.I., McMahan, C.D., and Westneat, M.W. (2017). Dirt-sifting Devilfish: Winnowing in the geophagine cichlid *Satanoperca daemon* and evolutionary implications. Zoomorphology. DOI: 10.1007/s00435-016-0335-6

Software

Weller, H.I. (2020). recolorize: Simplify and Remap Image Colors for Biological Analysis (ver. 0.9.000). CRAN Repository. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=recolorize

O'Sullivan, D., Weller, H.I., and Lord, N.P. Insect Color Database (ICDB). In development. https://insectcolor.com/

Weller, H.I. (2019). colordistance: Distance Metrics for Image Color Similarity (ver. 1.1.0). CRAN repository. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=colordistance

Weller, H.I. (2018). countcolors: Locates and Counts Pixels Within Color Range(s) in Images (ver. 0.9.1). CRAN Repository. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=countcolors

Presentations

Weller, H.I., López-Fernández, H., and Brainerd, E.L. Talk: Does feeding mediate life history tradeoffs in mouthbrooding cichlids? *Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology*, virtual conference.

Weller, H.I., (August 2021). Talk: Greater than the sum of their parts? Unpacking the "black box" of perceptual similarity using classical color pattern metrics. Living Light Early Career Reserachers, virtual conference.

Weller, H.I., Wham, D., Ezray-Wham, B., and Lord, N.P. (August 2021). Talk: Greater than the sum of their parts? Unpacking the "black box" of perceptual similarity using classical color pattern metrics. *Living Light Early Career Reserachers*, virtual conference.

Weller, H.I., Schwartz, S.T., Karan, E., and Lord, N.P. (Jan. 2021). Talk: Recolorize: a flexible R package for color classification. *Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology*, virtual conference.

Weller, H.I., López-Fernández, H., McMahan, C.D., and Brainerd, E.L. (Jan. 2020). Talk: The spandrels of Satan's perches: evidence for the co-optation of feeding traits in the convergent evolution of mouthbrooding in Neotropical cichlids. *Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, Austin, TX*.

Weller, H.I., López-Fernández, H., McMahan, C.D., and Brainerd, E.L. (Oct. 2019). Talk: Does mouthbrooding constrain or complement feeding morphology? *Regional Division of Vertebrate Morphology (Northeast), Newton, MA.*

Weller, H.I., Olsen, A., Camp, A.L., Hernandez, L.P., Manafzadeh, A.R., and Brainerd, E.L. (Jan. 2019). Talk: 3D-Intra-oral Prey Trajectories Indicate Distinct Phases in how Channel Catfish (Ictalurus punctatus, Siluriformes: Ictaluridae) Swallow Food. *International Congress of Vertebrate Morphology, Prague, CZ.*

Weller, H.I., Cohen, K.E., Gibb, A., and Brainerd, E.L. (Jan. 2019). Poster: Using tethers to measure food transport in a flatfish. Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, Tampa, FL.

Weller, H.I., Olsen, A., Camp, A.L., Hernandez, L.P., Manafzadeh, A.R., and Brainerd, E.L.(Jan. 2019). Talk: An XROMM study of intra-oral transport and swallowing in catfish. *Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, Tampa, FL.*

Weller, H.I. and Brainerd, E.L. (Oct. 2017). Talk: How do fish swallow food? Regional Division of Vertebrate Morphology (Northeast), Lowell, MA.

Weller, H.I., McMahan, C.D., and Westneat, M.W. (July 2016). Poster: Dirt-sifting devilfish: winnowing in eartheater cichlids. *American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists, New Orleans, LA*.

■ Invited talks, lectures, & workshops

June 2022 Workshop: Statistics for Biologists

University of Washington, Friday Harbor Laboratories (Friday Harbor, WA)

R workshop focusing on practical statistical approaches to messy biological data. Instructors: Matthew Kolmann and Cassandra Donatelli.

May 2022 Podcast: Naturalist Selections

American Society of Naturalists

Podcast interview about 2022 American Naturalist paper on the co-evolution of feeding and mouthbrooding in cichlids.

July 2020 Workshop: Phylogenetic Comparative Methods in R

University of Washington, Friday Harbor Laboratories (Friday Harbor, WA)

R workshop focusing on phylogenetic and comparative methods. Instructors: Matthew Kolmann

and Cassandra Donatelli.

July 2020 A field guide to statistics in organismal biology

> University of Washington, Friday Harbor Laboratories (Friday Harbor, WA) Guest lecture. Instructors: Matthew Kolmann and Cassandra Donatelli.

July 2020 Mouthbrooding morphologies in Neotropical cichlids

University of California Davis, Dept. of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology (Davis, CA)

Virtual seminar. Host: Peter Wainwright.

April 2020 Special Topics: Light, Color, and Vision in Biology (BIOL 7901/ENTM 7008)

> Louisiana State University, Dept. of Entomology and Dept. of Biology (Baton Rouge, LA) Guest lecturer (3 classes). Instructors: Nathan Lord (ENTM) & Brant Faircloth (BIOL).

December 2019 Workshop: R for Biologists

> Louisiana State University, Dept. of Entomology (Baton Rouge, LA) Organizer. Day-long workshop on data analysis and visualization in R.

Research experience

2017—Present PhD Candidate, Brainerd Lab; advisor: Elizabeth Brainerd

Brown University, Dept. of Ecology & Evolutionary Biology

Comparative morphology, kinematics, and biomechanics of mouthbrooding fishes; XROMM fish

feeding and transport.

September 2013—July Research assistant; advisor: Mark Westneat

2017 University of Chicago, Dept. of Organismal Biology & Anatomy

Quantitative color analysis; geometric morphometrics; high-speed video kinematics.

June 2015—September Jeff Metcalf Summer Research Fellow; advisor: Roger Hanlon

2015 Brown University, Dept. of Ecology & Evolutionary Biology

Hyperspectral imaging; image analysis pipelines; camouflage analyses.

June 2014—September Summer Research Fellow, Westneat Lab; advisor: Mark Westneat

2014 University of Chicago, Dept. of Organismal Biology & Anatomy

Ontogenetic scaling; biomechanical modeling; geometric morphometrics.

Teaching and outreach

June 2021 & July

2022

Instructor, Brown University, Summer@Brown Program (Providence, RI) Anatomy, Behavior, and Evolution: Fishy Solutions to Life Underwater

Intensive high school course including labs, assignments, and mentoring of final project (prepa-

ration of research proposals and presentations). 12 (2021) and 22 (2022) students.

August 2020 -

Teaching assistant, Brown University, Alpert Medical School (Providence, RI)

Present COVID-modified Human Anatomy (lecture and lab)

Restructuring the traditional gross anatomy curriculum, including remote/small group work and

prosection-based staggered labs.

September 2019

R User Group, Brown University, Dept. of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology (Providence, RI) - Present Organizing and running monthly R workshops for graduate and undergraduate students, focusing

on techniques for biological analysis (e.g., data organization, statistics, and visualization).

August 2019 -April 2020

Teaching assistant, Brown University, Alpert Medical School (Providence, RI)

Human Anatomy (lecture and lab)

Guiding medical students through cadaver-based human anatomy labs.

September 2018

Marine Science Club, Paul Cuffee High School (Providence, RI)

- Present Collaborating with high school teachers for weekly science activities with high school students.

September 2017

Teaching assistant, Brown University, Dept. of Ecology & Evolutionary Biology (Providence,

- Dec. 2017

Diversity of Life (lecture)

RI)

January 2015 Teaching assistant, University of Chicago, Dept. of Biological Sciences (Chicago, IL)

- April 2017 Presenting and supervising lab experiments; writing and grading assignments; lecturing; leading

paper discussions and review sessions; guiding dissection-based anatomy labs.

Genetic and Developmental Biology (lab & lecture) Multiscale Modeling of Biological Systems (lecture)

Molecular Biology of the Cell (lab)

Comparative Vertebrate Anatomy (lab & lecture)

June 2013 – September 2013

Animal care intern, New England Aquarium (Boston, MA)

Daily animal care and maintenance; visitor outreach; collection trips.

Skills

Coding R, Python (esp. OpenCV, Scrapy, & BioPython libraries), MATLAB, UNIX, MEL

Software Latex, Maya, FIJI/ImageJ, Horos, 3DSlicer, XMALab, Mesquite, Pandoc, Microsoft Office

Languages English (native), French (intermediate)

Lab: Biomedical Center 426, 171 Meeting St., Providence, RI 02906

Email: hannahiweller@gmail.com
Website: hiweller.rbind.io